(Sincro: wyxchari)
Keep away. Don't touch me. I'll obey.
离远点, 别碰我．我会服从的
What's that? What's happening!
那是什么？发生什么事了？
Doctor, that was it - that thing in the picture!
博士, 那就是了 - 图片里面的那个东西！
That was the claw! They're in control.
就是那个夹子！他们在管理员体内fixme
Take them out of here. They're condemned to the pits.
把他们带离这里！他们被判去矿坑！
Come on. Get out, all of you. Out! Get out!
快点, 出来, 你们所有人．出来！都出来！
Stand by work shift. Stand by in the pits.
站在工作班次旁边, 在矿坑里准备好
Work shift standing by.
工作班次待命
The strangers are being sent to you for pit labour.
Put them in the Danger Gang.
这些异乡人被派到你这里来采矿劳动．把他们安排进危险组
Your orders are correct, Pilot.
你的命令是正确的, 领航员
The strangers must be sent to explore the new gas reserves.
这些异乡人必须被派去探索新的瓦斯储备
They are dangerous people. They must be disciplined.
他们是危险人物, 比如接受纪律教育
Yes, Control.
是, 管理员
You will forget all that happened.
你会忘记所有发生的事情
Yes, Control.
是, 管理员
The Colony enjoys hard work and happiness.
殖民地享受辛苦工作和幸福
We will not tolerate the evil of such strangers.
我们不会容忍这些异乡人的邪恶
Yes, Control. You must serve the Colony.
是, 管理员．你们必须为殖民地服务
Keep watch on your friends, and if you see anything
suspicious, report to me immediately.
看着你的朋友, 如果你发现任何可疑, 立即向我报告
Yes, Pilot.
是, 领航员
We are all happy to work. We are all happy to work.
我们都幸福地工作．我们都幸福地工作
For the good of the Colony. Happy to work. Happy to work.
为了殖民地更美好．幸福地工作, 幸福地工作
Ooh!
噢！
What's the matter?
什么情况？
Dreadful. Did you hear that rhyme?
好吓人．你听到那个调子了吗？
The man who wrote that ought to be sent to
the Danger Gang - not us. Ha, ha, ha.
写那个的人应该被送到危险组 - 而不是我们, 哈哈哈
All right. That's enough.
好吧．到此为止了
Ah, are these the three strangers?
啊, 这就是那三个异乡人？
Yes.
是的
Yes, you might call us that.
是的, 你可以这么称呼我们
They've been allocated 176 shift.
他们已经轮了 176 班了
Oh, very good, Ola. I'll...
I'll recall the shift leader.
哦, 很好, Ola, 我去...我去召回轮班队长
What an extremely remarkable place.
What efficiency. What ever do you make?
一个多么了不起的地方, 多么高效．你做了什么吗fixme
Silence.
安静
I thought this was a mine.
You know, where you dig up coal?
我觉得这是一个矿．你们在哪里挖煤？
Ah, yes. But here, you see, the rock foundation
is a type of salt.
啊, 是的．不过是这里, 你看, 这里的岩基是一种盐
Now, at depths it generates gases over the years,
and these gases are extremely valuable.
现在, 在深处它这些年会产生瓦斯, 这些瓦斯非常有价值
Don't bother to explain to them. Just get them to work.
别费劲跟他们解释了．直接让他们去工作吧
Aye. Well, you don't send a lassie
and an old man down to dig.
是．不过, 你不应该派一个姑娘和一个老人下来挖矿
Old? What do you mean old? I'm not old, Jamie.
老？你说＂老＂是什么意思？我可不老, Jamie
You'll do as you're ordered.
你们得按命令行事
Here's the leader of their shift, sir.
这是他们这一班次的队长, 头儿
Very well. Report any irregularities to me.
很好, 有任何违规都向我报告
Medok. How did you get here?
Medok, 你怎么到这里来了？
Huh! They threw me out of the correction hospital.
Apparently I'm a hopeless case.
哼！他们把我扔出了矫治医院．显然我已经无可救药了
But why did they send you here?
但他们为什么把你送到这里来？
The one remaining punishment they could think of
- to work in the Danger Gang for life.
这是他们所能想到的最后一种惩罚 - 终身在危险组里工作
For life?
终身？
Oh, don't worry. You don't survive long in this atmosphere.
噢, 不用担心．在这样的空气里你不会活多久的
It's the gas. It gets everywhere.
It creeps into your lungs.
是这些瓦斯, 到处都是．它钻进你的肺里去
And when you're down there, you're right in the thick of it.
你如果到那下面去, 你就到了它最浓密的地方
Come on, Medok. Take them to their work.
快点, Medok, 带他们去工作
What's the hurry?
着什么急？
You don't want me to call the guard, do you?
你不想让我叫警卫吧, 想吗？
All right. All right. We're going.
But, we are entitled to a supervisor on this shift.
好吧, 好吧, 我们走．但我们这一班次得有一个监察员
Ah, yes. That's true.
啊, 是的, 这倒是
Yes. Well, I'm leaving this man.
是的．这样, 我把这个人留下
Hmm? Oh. Well, yes. I suppose that's all right.
唔？哦, 好吧, 行．我觉得这样行
But, it's much safer up here. Isn't it, Medok?
但, 这上面要安全得多, 是不是, Medok？
It is.
是的
Ah, I see. I'm perfectly capable of
working in the pit, thank you.
啊, 我明白了．我完全可以在矿坑里面工作, 谢谢你
Polly can have the safe job.
Polly 来承担安全工作吧
Uh, no. You stay up here. I wouldn't know what to do.
啊, 不, 你待在上面．我不知道该怎么做
Well, I'm not sure I understand all this machinery myself.
而且, 我不确定自己能否搞懂所有这些机器
Do you not think you might make better use
of the opportunity, Doctor?
你不觉得你也许能够更好地利用这次机会, 博士？
What do you mean? Oh, yes. Oh, yes. Yes.
I'll be supervisor.
你什么意思？哦, 是的, 哦, 是的, 是的．我来当监察员
What was all that?
那都是什么？
Nothing. Absolutely nothing.
没什么, 绝对没什么
Come on you two.
来吧你俩
Oh, you're going to issue them with masks, aren't you?
噢, 你会给他们派发面罩吧, 会吗？
You aren't taking them down there without any protection?
你不会是不给任何防护措施就带他们下去吧？
Surely you could have seen to that? Oh, ah, here.
想必你可以搞定那个？哦, 哈, 这里
You'd better take this, um... this checklist.
你最好带上这个, 还有..这个检查表
But I... I would have liked a mask.
但我...也想来一个面罩
This really is remarkable. Most interesting.
这真的是少有的经历．最有意思了
Yes. I suppose with a little adjustment...
是的, 我想只要进行一点小的调整...
Hello, Ben. Don't go. Come in. Don't be afraid.
你好, Ben．别走, 进来啊．不用害怕
I have nothing to be afraid of.
我没有什么可害怕的
No. Of course not. It wasn't your fault
you betrayed your friends.
没有, 当然没有．你背叛了你的朋友并不是你的错
The voices tell me what to do.
那些声音告诉我该做什么
The voices may not be right, Ben.
那些声音说的未必是对的, Ben
I do what I am told.
我按告诉我的规则行事
Yes, I know. That's why you're here, isn't it?
To spy on me.
是的, 我知道．那就是你来这里的原因, 对吧？为了监视我
What does Control want to know this time?
Won't you answer me?
管理员这次想知道什么？你不能答复我吗？
You know, Ben, this is very unlike you.
你知道吗, Ben, 这很不像你
I don't know what you mean. It is my duty.
我不知道你什么意思．这是我的职责
Hard for you to struggle against
the voices, isn't it, Ben?
你很难同那些声音抗争, 是不是, Ben?
I warn you, if you spy on the others,
watch out Jamie doesn't catch you.
我警告你, 如果你监视其他人, 小心别让 Jamie 抓到你
He's not so tolerant as I am.
他可不像我这么宽容
Hurry up. Put on your equipment.
快点, 戴上你们的设备
You shouldn't make lasses do the work of men.
你们不能让姑娘们来干男人的活
The Danger Gang will do as they are told.
It's a punishment for their failure to cooperate.
危险组让干什么就得干什么．这是对他们不肯合作的惩罚
We do all the dirty work. We go where the gas is worst.
我们来干脏活．我们去瓦斯最严重的地方
It's your own fault, Medok. If you obeyed Control...
这是你自己的错, Medok．如果你服从管理员...
All right. All right. Forget it.
打住, 打住．忘了吧
I prefer Control poisoning my lungs,
to their trying to poison my mind.
我更愿意管理员毒害我的肺, 而不是试图毒害我的思想
What's that?
那是什么？
It's a gas strike.
瓦斯泄漏了fixme
Go on! Help with the cable there. Go on.
Hurry up. That's the alarm.
继续！捋一下那里的管子, 继续．快点．警报响了fixme
What does he mean?
他什么意思？
He means they've struck so much gas,
they can't channel it off.
他意思时他们挖掘出很多瓦斯, 不能把它们抽走
When it reaches a certain density, that alarm bell goes.
当达到一定浓度时, 警报就会响
Hurry up! Get that cable to the strike.
快点！把管子拿到泄漏点
Come on. Quickly.
加油, 快点
Quickly. Come on. Pull there.
Pull, all of you. Pull. Pull.
快点, 加油．拉那里, 拉啊, 你们所有人．拉, 拉
Polly!
Polly!﻿
Leave her. Get that cable to the strike.
别管她了, 把管子拿到泄漏点去
Get her away from here. Away.
带她离开这里, 离开
Jamie, the head of the cable. Got it? Right.
Jamie, 管子的那头．拿住了, 好
Put your masks on. They're in your pocket.
戴上你的面罩, 在你的口袋里
Right. Now, help me with this.
Hold it. Hold it, Jamie. Right.
好了, 现在, 帮我弄一下这个．稳住, 稳住, Jamie．好了
What's it all for?
这有什么作用？
It's a poisonous gas which we mine,
from the bowels of this planet,
我们从这个星球里面挖掘的是一种有毒气体
which kills us if we breathe it.
如果我们吸进去, 会害死我们的
No one knows what it's used for.
没人知道这东西用来做什么的
Yes. Now, one must assume that the relative connection
is constant. Now, let me see.
好了, 现在, 我们得假设相对连接是恒定的．现在, 让我看看
Ah! Yes. I think that's right.
I should give myself ten out of ten.
啊, 对了！我觉得这样对了．我应该给自己十分
Oh, you did give me a turn.
哦, 你fixme
Where did you find it?
你在那里找到的？
What?
什么？
The formula.
方程式
In my head. You know.
从我的大脑里, 知道不
Don't lie. That is a secret
known only to three people in the Colony.
别撒谎．这是一项秘密, 这个殖民地只有三个人知道
And you're one of them?
而你是其中的一个？
Naturally. And you're not asking me to believe
that in a few moments you have been able to...
当然．你不是要我相信, 在顷刻之间你就能够...
...work out a formula which it has taken
our combined computers years to perfect?
推导出这个方程式把, 我们可是耗费多台电脑数年时间才完善出来
It does seem rather a tall order.
看起来的确是个高阶的
Yes, of course. I know what you've done.
You've broken into our secret files, haven't you?
是的, 当然了．我知道你干了什么．你偷看了我们的机密文件, 是吧？
I wouldn't know how to do that. Take a look.
我不知道怎么干那个．你看看
Well, you must have seen the document.
That's the exact computation.
是了, 你肯定看过文档了, 这个计算过程是一样的
Really? Huh. In that case...
真的吗？哈, 这样的话...
Do you really mean to say
that you worked that out by yourself?
你真的是想说, 你完全自己推导出来的？
Well, I did have a little assistance.
哦, 我的确靠了一点小小的协助
Yes, I thought so. Who was it?
是的, 我也觉得．是谁？
Oh, no, no, no. Oh, no. No person. No.
噢, 不, 不．噢, 不．不是人．不是
I simply mean that I took readings from the various dials.
我只是说我从多个仪表盘上采集了数据
They appeared to be related, so I worked out
the principle that controls them.
它们看起来是有关联的．所以我推导出来了控制它们的原理
It was simple really. Like doing a sum backwards.
其实很简单, 真的．就像倒着求和一样
Backwards?
倒着？
Yes. You know. Given the answer, what's the question?
是的．你知道, 就是给定答案, 找出问题
Wipe it away. Get it off there before anybody else sees it.
擦掉吧．从这里下去fixme, 以免有别人看到了
Oh, well. If you insist.
噢, 好吧, 你非得坚持的话
Ho, ho. There now. If anyone follows that formula,
there'll be an almighty explosion
呵呵, 看看．如果有人按这个方程式fixme, 就会引发一场巨大的爆炸
x to the power of y is derivative 2 3's of 6!
Get it off.
What are they doing?
他们在做什么？
We call that probing.
我们管这个叫做探测
They're not looking for more gas?
他们不是在找寻更多的瓦斯吧？
Oh, yes. We never stop!
哦, 是的, 我们从未停止！
There's a door here. Where's it lead to?
这里有道门, 它通向哪里？
I've no idea. To my knowledge, those doors were never opened.
我不知道．据我的了解, 那些门从来没有打开过
Could be an old shaft.
可能是一个旧的竖井
Why would it need such a new door? And so strong?
为什么它需要一道这么新的门？还这么结实？
Hey, look out!
嘿, 小心！
Ah, you've made the connection?
啊, 你搞定连接了？
Of course. Otherwise you wouldn't be here.
当然, 否则你不会在这里
Now, be careful, Medok. There are other places
worse than the Danger Gang, you know.
现在, 小心点, Medok．有些地方比危险组更严重, 你知道吧
This is a high pressure strike.
You are going to need a stronger screw than this.
这是fixme
Don't touch it.
别碰它
I know what I'm doing.
我知道我在做什么
He's fainted.
他晕倒了
Aye. He must have.
是, 他肯定是
What's the matter? What has happened to him?
怎么回事？他怎么了？
He's had a wee whiff of the gas.
他吸进去了一小口这种瓦斯
Get him up. I'll look after him.
扶他起来, 我来照看他
Yeah. It's all right, mate. Hang on.
好, 应该没事了, 伙计．坚持住
How long do you think Ben was watching us?
你觉得 Ben 监视我们多久了？
I don't know.
我不知道
Do you think he saw you take the keys?
你觉得他看到你拿走钥匙了吗？
Well, if he did, we're in trouble.
哦, 如果他看到了, 我们就有麻烦了
Yes.
是的
It just means we'll have to make use of them quick as we can.
这只意味着我们必须得尽快使用它们
But where, Jamie. And how?
但在哪儿用, Jamie, 怎么用？
Let's try that wee door first. Come on.
让我们先试试那道小门, 快来
Give me the word if anybody comes.
如果有谁来就吱一声
Right. Lookout, OK.
好, 小心．好了
Hey, you two, give us a hand.
嘿, 你们俩, 帮我一把
Um, all right. I'd better go.
唔, 没事, 我最好走了
Just a minute Polly. This key's turning. Oh.
等一下 Polly．钥匙在转动, 噢
Good luck.
祝你好运
Aye. It fits. Come on, Pol.
是, 钥匙对上了．快来, Pol
Come on. Here everybody. Lend a hand.
快点, 所有人, 搭我一把
What's that?
那是什么？
It's impossible.
这不可能
Is it more gas?
还是瓦斯吗？
No. It's an escape. That bell means that
someone has escaped down here.
不是．是个出口．钟声说明有人从下面逃走了
It's Jamie.
是 Jamie
Your friend? That door! I'm going with him.
你的朋友吗？那个门？我跟他走
Hey wait! Don't leave me down here.
嘿等等！别把我一个人扔在这下面
We couldn't have an alarm.
It's impossible. No one ever escapes.
我们不能拉警报．这是不可能的, 没人能够逃走
Calling Pit Guard. Close exits to all gas shafts.
呼叫矿坑警卫．关闭所有瓦斯竖井的出口
Stand by. A prisoner has escaped. Shoot on sight.
请待命．有囚徒逃走了．看见就开枪
But, if no one can escape...
但是, 如果没有人能逃走...
My keys! My keys! They were on my tunic.
我的钥匙！我的钥匙！它们本来在我束腰外衣上的
You must have dropped them.
你肯定弄丢它们了
Special guards to cover all exits to the old shaft.
特别警卫去负责旧竖井的所有出口
With Pilot's permission,
they may have to go on forbidden ground.
有领航员的许可, 他们可以进入紧地
Jamie? Jamie? Jamie? Ah!
Jamie? Jamie? Jamie? 啊!
Hello? Who's there?
哈罗？谁在哪儿？
No permission is granted for the guard to
go on forbidden ground.
警卫没有获得进入禁地的权限
Repeat, no permission. They are not to cover
the exit to the old shaft.
重复, 没有权限．他们不得去把守旧竖井的出口
This is in use at this moment by Control.
当前它正在被管理员使用
No one is to go in or near the old shaft. Top priority.
任何人不可进入或者靠近旧竖井．最高优先级
They seem very emphatic about that.
他们似乎特别强调了那个
Control knows best.
管理员清楚怎样最好
But what if your prisoner escapes that way?
What will happen to you?
但是如果你的犯人往那边逃跑了呢？你会怎么样？
I shall be punished.
我会被惩罚
Well, aren't you going to do something about it?
啊, 你不打算对此做点什么吗？
Control knows best.
管理员清楚怎样最好
Who has escaped anyway?
究竟是谁逃跑了？
We shall soon find out.
我们很快就能搞明白
It is Jamie.
是 Jamie
How do you know that, Ben?
你怎么知道的, Ben?
I saw him take the keys.
我看见他拿走了钥匙
And you didn't report it?
而你当时没有报告？
No.
没有
Why not?
为什么没有？
I don't know. I don't seem to be able to think straight.
我不知道．我似乎不能清晰地思考
Ben, you're recovering. I always thought
you were a tough customer. Well done!
Ben, 你开始恢复了．我一直都觉得你是一个硬汉．做得好
Control knows best.
管理员清楚怎样最好
You don't seem very sure.
你似乎并不是太确信
Jamie took those keys. I must report him!
Jamie 拿走了钥匙, 我必须检举他！
Doctor, you know what's happened?
博士, 你知道发生了什么吗？
Yes. Jamie's got free.
知道, Jamie 逃走了
By my calculations he's got a very good chance.
根据我的计算他有很大的机会
Hold that for me, will you?
帮我拿着这个, 好吗？
What do you mean?
你什么意思？
Well, as I understand it, Jamie's in the old shaft.
哦, 根据我的理解, Jamie 在旧的竖井里
Yes. That's right.
是, 说对了
And for reasons of their own,
Control don't want anyone there.
而由于他们自己的一些原因, 管理员不想让任何人进去
It's forbidden territory.
那是个禁区
- So you think he'll be all right?
- I don't know.
- 所以你觉得他会没事？ - 我不知道
I'll be able to tell you
when I've tested this to see how lethal it is.
等我测试一下这个看它有致命, 我才能告诉你
But what's that got to do with Jamie?
但那个跟 Jamie 有什么关系？
On this planet it's got a lot to do with everybody.
在这个星球上, 它跟每个人都有很大关系
- There now. Yes.
- Oh, Doctor. What on earth are you doing?
- 现在, 是了  - 噢, 博士, 你到底在干什么？
I'm trying to analyse this gas,
and I'm not having very much luck.
我试图在分析这些瓦斯, 但并运气并不是太好
Is that the same stuff
that we've been pumping out of the pits?
是跟我们从矿坑里抽出来的一样的东西吗？
Yes. And they go to great efforts to get it.
The question is why?
是的．他们费很大劲去采集它．问题是, 为什么？
Ssh! Somebody's coming.
嘘！ 有人来了
Ooh! Mustn't find this.
噢！不能发现这个
Oh, the Pilot's not here. Let me help you.
哦, 导航员不再这里．让我来帮你吧
No.
不
Always lend a helping hand.
A willing friend makes the task lighter.
永远伸出援助之手．一个乐于助人的朋友会帮任务变得轻松
I'll wait for the Pilot. If I'm going to tell anybody...
我要等领航员．如果我告诉任何人...
You are, aren't you?
你会的, 对吗？
I don't know what I'm going to do.
我不知道我应该做什么
I got these voices in my head.
Sometimes I just think I'm having a bad dream.
我脑袋里面有这些声音, 有时我觉得我正在做恶梦
But the voices are here to help us.
They are our friends.
但那些声音是来帮助我们的, 它们是我们的朋友
That's it. What about my friends?
对了, 我的朋友们怎么样了
I'll see you are reported for this.
If this were not an emergency...
fixme 如果这不是紧急情况
The bell stopped. Why has it stopped?
钟声停掉了．为什么停掉了
Because, young lady, the emergency is over.
因为, 年轻的女士, 紧急状况已经结束了
Does that mean he's been caught?
那就是说他被抓住了
It means they're closing in on him.
这意味着他们正在向他逼近
Thank you. But, why didn't you tell this to Officia?
谢谢你．但是, 为什么你不把这个告诉官方？
You told me to report back to you.
你告诉我报告给你的
I see. Very well. The stranger who has escaped is
in the old shaft. Control will now give instructions.
我明白了, 很好．逃跑的异乡人在旧竖井里．管理员会给出指示的
All guards will leave the area of the old shaft.
所有警卫得离开旧竖井区域
No one must go near it, even in search of the stranger.
无人可以靠近它, 即使是为了搜寻异乡人
Do not approach its exit or entrance. Do not go in.
不要靠近它的出口或者入口, 不要进入
Officials are to stand by at the gas centre.
官员们到瓦斯中心待命
We will obey, Control.
我们服从, 管理员
Gas centre standing by. What transfers do you wish made?
瓦斯中心待命中．你期望传输什么？
Prepare for gas to be diverted into the old shaft.
Inspect connection immediately and report back.
准备将瓦斯分流到旧竖井中．立即检查连接并回报结果
The old shaft. Doctor, that's where Jamie is!
旧竖井．博士, 那是 Jamie 所在的地方！
They're going to pour this gas in the old shaft
- gas they value above all else.
他们打算将瓦斯灌入旧竖井去 - 他们看得比什么都珍贵的瓦斯
What do you make of that, Polly?
你有什么结论, Polly?
For goodness sake, Doctor. What are you going on about?
老天啊, 博士, 你这是要干什么?
Don't you see? Control are not pouring this poisonous
gas into the old shaft to kill Jamie.
你没明白吗？管理员并不是要把有毒瓦斯灌入竖井去毒死 Jamie
They've quite another reason.
他们肯定有其它原因
Doctor, you've got to do something to help him.
博士, 你得做点什么帮助他
Before we act, we must think.
我们行动之前, 必须先思考
Now, the Macra that have come to the surface of this planet
现在, Macra 已经跑到这个星球的表面了
have not found sufficient gas in the atmosphere,
它们在大气中没有找到足够的瓦斯
so they've had to get somebody to
pump it up from down below.
于是他们不得不让人把它从下面抽上来
But, if it's life and death to them, why do they waste it?
但是, 如果这瓦斯对他们性命攸关, 他们为什么要浪费掉它？
- Why divert it into the old shaft?
- That's obvious, Polly. Obvious.
- 为什么把它分流到旧竖井里去？  - 这很显然, Polly, 显然．
Because there's something trapped down there
they wish to keep alive.
因为那下面有某种东西他们想让它活着
Officia reporting. All connections have been tested.
They are all one hundred percent serviceable.
官方报告, 所有连接已经测试过了, 都是 100% 可用的
Transfer of all gases may now be made to the old shaft.
所有瓦斯的传输将可进入旧竖井
Stand by for action.
准备开始行动
The Colony. The Colony is happy to obey.
The Colony is happy to obey.
殖民地．殖民地乐于服从, 殖民地乐于服从
We've got to help him.
我们得帮助他
I'm doing my best, Polly. I'm thinking at top speed.
我在尽可能, Polly．在用最高速度思考
There's a pattern involved here - a combination of pipes.
If one were to follow this one...
这里有某种规律 - 管道的组合．如果有人顺着这个...
Stand by gas Officia. All flow is to be channelled
through systems seven and eleven.
瓦斯官员待命．所有气体导向第７和第11系统
Seven and eleven. Now which are they?
7 和 11．都是哪个？
All channels are ready.
所有管道已经就绪
Prepare to turn on at half blast.
准备打开到一半压力
All ready.
都就绪了
Now!
开动！
Seven and eleven. If that's the system in use,
it must go from here round up to there.
7 和 11．如果那是在用的系统, 它肯定是从这里绕上去到那里
Officia is to increase pressure.
官方准备加大压力
Doctor, quickly.
博士, 快！
Polly, I think I've found the gas flow.
Polly, 我想我已经找到了瓦斯流向
The pressure's being increased.
压力正在增加
Turn on full pressure now.
现在压力全开
Full pressure in action!
已经开到最大压力！